Guide to the Edward Robie Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Edward Robie Papers
1852-1896
RG 293
Yale University Divinity School Library
5.75
(14 boxes)
The collection documents Robie's professional work at Andover Theological Seminary and as a Congregational minister in Greenland, New Hampshire from 1852 to 1917.
Biographical / Historical
Edward Robie was born in Gorham, Maine in 1821. He graduated from Bowdoin College in 1840 and from Andover Theological Seminary in 1843. He studied in Germany during the next three years, at the universities of Halle and Berlin. When he returned to the U.S. he taught ancient and modern languages at Gorham Academy, 1846-1848. He returned to Andover to become Librarian and Instructor of Sacred Literature at the Seminary, positions he held until 1851. Robie was ordained to the Congregational ministry at Greenland, NH, on February 25, 1852 and remained as pastor of the Greenland church until his death in 1917.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was given to Andover Newton Theological School by the Community Congregational Church of Greenland, New Hampshire in 1987 and transferred to the Yale Divinity Library in 2017.
Scope and Contents
The Edward Robie Papers document his professional work. Almost all material is undated, but it could be presumed that the manuscripts span his pastoral career at Greenland, NH, 1852-1917. The collection includes an autobiography (1868), European travel journal (1896), letters (2 items), sermons (arranged by biblical text) addresses, unpublished literary manuscripts, and book reviews (arranged in alphabetical order).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series:
Series I. Autobiography
Series II. Travel Journal
Series III. Correspondence
Series IV. Sermons
Series V. Addresses
Series VI. Unpublished Literary Manuscripts
Series VII. Book Reviews
- Autobiography, Series I
  - Autobiography, 1868 (Box 1)
- Travel Journal, Series II
  - European Journal, 1896 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Series III
  - Edward Robie to the Congregational Church and Society in Greenland, N.H, 1852 January 16 (Box 1)
  - Robie to Church and People, 1868 April 4 (Box 1)
- Sermons, Series IV
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged by scriptural text. For a full listing of texts, see the original finding aid for the collection, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Genesis - 2 Samuel (Box 1)
  - 1 Kings - Psalm 44: 1, 3 (Box 2)
  - Psalm 46:8-11 - Proverbs 8:15 (Box 3)
  - Proverbs 8:15, 16 - Jeremiah (Box 4)
  - Lamentations - Matthew 11:6 (Box 5)
  - Matthew 11:27 - Mark 9:50 (Box 6)
  - Mark 11:21, 22 - John 1:16 (Box 7)
  - John 1:16 - John 17:8 (Box 8)
  - John 17:17 - Romans 10:15 (Box 9)
  - Romans 12:1 - 2 Corinthians (Box 10)
  - Galatians - 1 Timothy (Box 11)
  - 2 Timothy - 2 Peter (Box 12)
  - 1 John - Revelations (Box 13)
- Addresses, Series V
  - Dedicatory Prayer, Epping, 1885 (Box 13)
  - Charge to the Pastor (Box 13)
  - Expository Address on the Sermon on the Mount (Box 13)
  - Graduation Addresses, 1879–1902 (Box 13)
  - Graduation Address, Andover/Exeter (Box 13)
  - Historical Sketch of the Church (Box 13)
  - Lecture Before the YMCA (Box 14)
  - Sin (Box 14)
  - Some Lessons of History, to the Members of the Bradeshill(?) Academy (Box 14)
  - Some Lessons of History, to the Pascataqua Club (Box 14)
  - fragments (7 folders) (Box 14)
- Unpublished Literary Manuscripts, Series VI
  - Africa (Box 14)
  - Baptism (Box 14)
  - The Bible (Box 14)
  - Biblical Psychology (Box 14)
  - The Chinese Empire (Box 14)
  - Day of Public Fasting and Prayer (Box 14)
  - Lecture on·Democracy (Box 14)
  - Divine Truth (Box 14)
  - Divinity of Christ and His Eternal Dependence Upon the Father (Box 14)
  - Doctrine of the Holy Spirit (Box 14)
  - Genesis: An Outline Study of Man (Box 14)
  - Genesis: Man in the Image of God (Box 14)
  - History of Greenland, N.H. (Box 14)
  - The Holy Spirit (Box 14)
  - Job (Box 14)
  - Joseph (Box 14)
  - Look Aloft: A Meditation at Sea (Box 14)
  - Manners (Box 14)
  - Martyrdom (Box 14)
  - Mental Philosophy (Box 14)
  - Methodism (Box 14)
  - The New Revision (Box 14)
  - Parochial Evangelization (Box 14)
  - Piscataqua Centenary (Box 14)
  - Piscataqua Mission Society (Box 14)
  - Preach the Word (Box 14)
  - Preaching the Word (Box 14)
  - Present State of O.T. Criticism (Box 14)
  - Review of Temperance Work (Box 14)
  - Sabbath School (Box 14)
  - Sacred Medicine (Box 14)
  - Song of Solomon (Box 14)
  - Sunday Afternoon (poem) (Box 14)
  - There is a Wideness in God's Mercy (poem) (Box 14)
  - Thoughts on Missions (Box 14)
  - The Trinity (Box 14)
  - The Trinity (the divinity of Christ) (Box 14)
  - Truth of the Scriptures (Box 14)
  - Understanding of Christ (Box 14)
  - Unity of the Church (Box 14)
  - The Value of the Old Testament (Box 14)
  - What is Religion? (Box 14)
  - World War I (Box 14)
  - Ordination paper, 1852 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 14)
- Book Reviews, Series VII
  - Briggs, Charles Augustus. The Ethical Teachings of Jesus and Whither? A Theological Question (Box 14)
  - Darwin, Charles. The Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection (Box 14)
  - Hanna, William. Memoir of Life and Writings of Thomas Chalmers (Box 14)
  - Harnack, Adolf von. Wesen der Christenthismus (Box 14)
  - Liddon, Henry Parry. The Divinity of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ (Box 14)
  - Root, Jean.Christie. Edward Irving: Man, Preacher, Prophet (Box 14)